Shravani Nimbolkar

+15105707497 nimbolkarshravani.github.io | nimbolkarshravani@gmail.com | linkedin.com/in/shravaninimbolkar | https://github.com/nimbolkarshravani

SUMMARY

Dedicated Data Scientist with over **4 years** of experience in building and deploying Machine learning and Deep learning models with proficiency in **Python, SQL**, cloud technologies, Tableau data visualization, NLP, NLG, **docker, Kubernetes**, and variety of AI frameworks(Keras/TensorFlow/PyTorch). I specialize in extracting actionable insights from large structured and unstructured datasets.

SKILLS

- Languages: Python, SQL, R, C++, Frontend: HTML, CSS, JS;
- Frameworks: Pandas, Numpy, Sklearn, TensorFlow, Pytorch, Keras, Regression, Ensemble techniques, CatBoost, Statsmodel, Simple Transformers, Streamlit, OpenCV, NLTK, Flask, Git, RapidMiner, PySpark, Pypfopt, GCP, Docker, Kubernetes, H2O, BigQueryML, Langchain, Gemini Pro, ChatGPT, Prompt Engineering;
- Dashboard and Database: PowerBI, Tableau, SQL Workbench, Looker Studio, Google analytics dashboard, SaS, MS Excel
- Certification: MTS Introduction to Python, Google Analytics, Coursera: Deep Learning Specialization, Artificial Intelligence: Ethics & Societal Challenges etc

EXPERIENCE

Data Scientist | Biomotivate | Pittsburgh, USA

Oct 2023 - Present

- Designing and fine-tuning Deep Learning models to predict early treatment dropouts using physiological data from patients at a rehabilitation centre.
- Utilizing **PowerBI** for data analysis and Python to employ time series analysis techniques to fine-tune 'Empatica' E4 Electro-Dermal Activity (EDA) data at different frequencies. Led data dives to analyze Empatica E4 Electro-Dermal Activity (EDA) data, conducting in-depth hypothesis testing to gain a nuanced understanding of physiological responses for improving model's performance.

Data Science Intern | OmniThink.ai | San Francisco, USA

May 2023 - Aug 2023

- Optimized **SQL** queries in BigQueryML on a dataset of 14.5K rows resulting in 20% reduction in query execution time. Trained and deployed ARIMA PLUS and ARIMAX timeseries model on **GCP Cloud environment**. Developed interactive visualization dashboards on **Looker Studio** to convey actionable insights to stakeholders.
- Used BERT/GPT **API** for **Sentiment analysis** on product reviews to leverage the forecast. Performed statistical analysis and hypothesis testing for feature selection and VIF technique in Statsmodel to mitigate multicollinearity.
- Used hyperparameter tuning to reduce the mean error by 6% compared to baseline ARIMA PLUS model.
- Built and managed data pipelines in Dataflow to streamline analytics workflows in real-time.

Associate Analyst | Schlumberger | Pune, India

Aug 2021 - Jul 2022

- Maintained 98%+ uptime for 150+ applications across the organization through monitoring and troubleshooting using Dynatrace and SAP Solman eradicating 75% critical issues. Leveraged Power Automate to automate 50% of documentation workflows, streamlining processes and increasing operational efficiency.
- Created and deployed real-time PowerBI dashboards for stakeholders to track application's performance metrics and KPIs for informed decision making.
- Played a critical role during system outages by promptly reporting alerts, collaborating with SREs, product owners and application teams, and coordinating resolution
 efforts. Demonstrated strong collaboration skills in a high-pressure environment.

Machine Learning Intern | Centre for Development of Advanced Computing | Mumbai, India

Sep 2020 - Mar 2021

- Researched about LLMs and Implemented a BERT classifier in Simple Transformers on Liar Liar (comprising 12.K rows) and PolitiFact(comprising 21K rows) dataset.
- Performed text pre-processing **NLP tasks** and extracted out stylistic attributes of the text like length, grammar, word frequency along with like stance detection, emotion and **toxicity** analysis and studied their correlation with the target variable to refine the prediction.
- Fine-tuned the BERT model on 80% data which yielded an accuracy of 82%, achieved a 4% increase in accuracy compared to the baseline model.

EDUCATION

University of California, Berkeley

Aug 2023

MS in Analytics | GPA 3.6 | Vice-President of Technology @ Analytics Consulting Organization at Berkeley

Pune University

Jul 2021

Bachelor of Computer Engineering | CGPA: 9.0/10.0

Courses: DSA, Database Management, Software engineering & Project management, Al & Robotics, Data Analytics, Data Mining & Warehouse, Machine Learning

NOTABLE PROJECTS

Chat With PDF | GitHub

Jan 2024

- Developed a **Chatbot** for interactive querying of information from multiple PDF documents using Google Gemini Pro and LangChain. Incorporated **NLG** techniques to enhance the conversational aspect of the Chatbot, providing users with natural humanlike responses.
- Implemented efficient text summarization and indexing with Google Generative AI Embeddings, ensuring accurate information retrieval from large datasets.
- Designed and implemented a streamlined web application using Streamlit, enhancing the user experience for asking questions and receiving detailed responses.
 Leveraged Python, Streamlit, PyPDF2, LangChain, Google Generative AI, and FAISS to create an innovative solution for conversational PDF interaction.

Analysing Customer Reviews | Uhack Sentiment 2.0: Decode Code words | Rank 5

Jan 2022

- Analyzed customer review dataset consisted of 6000+ rows and 12 different labels about product usability, functionality, installation, design and aesthetics etc.
- Performed text pre-processing **NLP** techniques and fine-tuned an ensemble of 8 RoBERTa models for multi-label classification
- Used multi-label stratified cross-validation for hyperparameters tuning and minimizing the logloss.
- Ranked 5th on the leaderboard (logloss=2.781), demonstrating the effectiveness of the Transformer ensemble approach.

Lung Disease Prediction | CXRDiagnosis | 1st Prize | GitHub | Book chapter

Jun 2021

- Built a classifier called MetaEfficientNet trained on Chest X Ray image dataset having an accuracy of 97% with 3 classes; Pneumonia, COVID19 & Normal.
- Used Few shot learning approach to further train the model on limited data. Used Metric-based Siamese net consisting of two EfficientNetB0 as sister networks and head model **CNN** to learn the image **embeddings** in feature space.
- Achieved an accuracy of 85.5% for 6 newly introduced classes of lung diseases; successfully **docker**-containerized the model and deployed web app using flask and **Salesforce Heroku**; led a team of 3 and won 1st prize among 23 project teams.

DELOITTE Machine Learning Challenge | Risky Loan Defaulter Prediction | Top 3% | Notebook

Jan 2021

Developed an ensemble of CatBoost, Light GBM and XGBoost trained on a dataset of 67k rows, 35 features to predict Loan defaulters to achieve log loss of 0.36.

HACKATHONS

- Performed feature selection and used SMOTE, KNN and Down sampling to handle class imbalances to further reduce the loss to 0.34
- Finally performed error analysis to understand the model and quantized risk using Conformal Prediction

AgroML (Crop Weed Detection using AI)

OTHER PROJECTS

- Sensor AI (Human activity recognition using Smart phone sensors)
- Customer Segmentation (Consumer behaviour Analysis)
- GOOGLE | BigQuery ML Data Centric AI Competition | Feb 2023 | Rank 23
- **ZS** | ACE A THON | <u>Top 10</u>
- INNOVATE FOR SMART PCMC | 2nd Prize